hey everyone this is dalia from ecom ops
today i want to talk about if you're
running an ecommerce brand why you
should always consider fulfilling from
china shipping directly to your
customers even if you're using or
considering using a us3pl or local3pl
we're going to talk about some of the
benefits of fulfilling from china and
some real numbers and how it can help
your business we're going to talk about
some of the reasons why in the last
couple of years china fulfillment has
gotten so much better than before and
then we're going to talk about some tips
on best utilizing china fulfillment for
your business now before we get started
i really do want to emphasize that we're
not just talking about drop shipping
here we're talking about shipping and
fulfilling from china whether you're
drop shipping or not all right let's get
started
the benefits of using china fulfillment
are very obvious first
shipping is pretty efficient you're
going to be able to get as fast as 5 to
10 calendar days shipping to the us in
many markets around the world you're
gonna be able to experience extremely
short lead times from your factory to a
fulfillment center in china which means
that you can hold 90 percent uh less
inventory or more actually and you're
going to be able to scale much more
flexibly and have much lower risk in
your cash investment in inventory and
you're going to be able to ship globally
very profitably and all this is probably
going to be cheaper than
any kind of local fulfillment service
but let's actually do some math so let's
start with
the lead time question let's assume that
you have a product that you're paying
three dollars per unit for in terms of
cogs let's assume that you
uh are planning to sell or are selling
100 orders of it per day and let's
assume that there's no factory lead
times or we're just factoring in the uh
freight lead time in the traditional
model you might be using sea freight now
c3 these days you got to plan for maybe
60 days or so so to be completely safe
you probably should plan around 90 days
of inventory now the simple math is you
plan for 90 days of inventory that's 90
times 100 orders per day times three
dollars on average uh for each unit
that's 27 000
9000 units in inventory that you have to
plan ahead and therefore risk your cash
and tie it up in inventory to support uh
your order volume in the other extreme
if you're fulfilling from china anywhere
in china to anywhere else it's going to
take a couple days let's assume three
days for this purpose and you might want
to plan for five days of stock to be
safe and the math then is three dollars
per unit times five days worth of
inventory times 100 orders per day and
that's only going to be 1500
of inventory risk upfront at any one
time i mean that's more than a 90
reduction in how much inventory you have
to hold so it's a huge difference in the
amount of cash flow that you need to
hold and in a similar vein the much
shorter lead time means that you have
much more flexibility in scaling up
let's just take the same scenario you're
selling at 100 orders per day and you
have 9 000 units planned for 90 days now
let's just say your ads crush it and you
start selling a thousand units per day
well then you only have nine days in
inventory all right so what do you do
you sell out and therefore you have to
wait 90 days again potential or 60 days
again to get more inventory or do you
choose to ram down which is obviously
opportunity cost lost in potential sales
whereas this is not a problem at all in
china because the lead times are three
days you're planning for five days at a
time so you can very flexibly scale up
in just days and allow you to scale up
to thousands of orders per day within
you know weeks time without really
worrying about having to shut down or
having to lose potential sales now we're
actually going to run through some
scenario analysis of different options
of different example products and
comparing between using u.s fulfillment
and also china fulfillment and i just
want to give a little bit more
background here so
for the u.s fulfillment piece we're
actually going to compare versus shipbob
so shipbob they actually have a
calculator that we can actually list
below so this is literally the cost that
if you actually input into shipbot
prices and this is for their standard
rates now i will quickly say that uh
shipbox standard shipping is okay like
if you use shipbot before their standard
uh cheaper option it's gonna be three to
seven business days or something so
roughly speaking it's like you know one
or two weeks actually so it's not that
fast because they use a combination usps
and also a cheaper economical services
from fedex and ups for example but you
know this is just the standard option
they have this is obviously not like
their two-day shipping which is a lot
more expensive we're going to compare
versus three different example products
now i'm not going to be able to share
the products with you but these are
actual products they're actual weights
of the products and and their actual
cogs value as well all right and just a
quick note is that this data is uh as of
the end of february or so or early march
all right so if you're watching this
video much later than that and these
numbers are not that accurate well you
know why because a lot of these numbers
especially freight and shipping prices
will change all right so i'm going to go
through this analysis uh
we have three example products one that
weighs 30 grams one that weighs 140
grams and one that weighs 550 grams to
show you a range of the different types
of product weights and here they are in
ounces and their example cogs values as
well so first let's start shipping uh
from shipbop so we just plugged these
numbers in and we got these numbers now
in u.s fulfillment one thing that you
have to know is that there is going to
be a range of prices based on the weight
so
we have the range here but we're just
going to put the average here just for
simplicity this is shipping to the us
within the us from shipbob assuming it's
their u.s like la location for example
and the shipping time let's assume four
to twelve days or so and this is very
accurate because this is their standard
economy shipping around four to twelve
calendar days one thing that
some folks don't realize when they
compare costs is that well
your products have to get to the us in
the first place so you have to consider
the freight costs as well and we
actually laid out four different options
for freight uh two different types of
air
one is just economy air freight and the
other type of error is just using
something like dhl to be faster but
obviously more expensive
and and the freight times are going to
be different as well and there's also
going to be an economy c
and there's also going to be a faster
sea freight kind of option and obviously
all of these are different prices so
these are all real prices that uh your
supplier or freight forwarder will
probably quote you for this kind of
product one thing to note is that we are
assuming just a relatively medium-sized
batch of like say a thousand units now
these calculations do change if you're
actually sending a container full but
we're not talking about that right now
we're talking about maybe a couple
thousand units right now we're gonna
assume that there's no customs fees for
some products a lot of products you have
to consider customs as well but right
now we're going to assume no customs
just to simplify things and we'll run
some numbers with the customs as well
and this is right here
a total cost then of if you're using u.s
fulfillment so this is simply the cost
of each of these freight options plus
the cost of shipping within the us uh
plus the customs which right now we just
assume is zero for now all right so
these are the cost shipping uh using a
usbl for different freight options now
here are the costs that we would quote a
potential client shipping directly from
china using e-comm ops
there are three lines that we can use
one is going to be five to ten days a
calendar days that's the express line a
regular line is cheaper it's gonna be
five to fourteen days or so and there's
an ordinary line that's going to be six
to 16 days or so so we're not going to
compare where's the express line we're
gonna compare versus our regular lines
the most comparable and uh we're going
to compare versus this now if we
actually look at this i mean this is
basically what the difference is if you
are fulfilling from china versus the
calculations that we just did fulfilling
from the u.s uh assuming the freight as
well so as you see here so so green is
where it's actually cheaper to fulfill
from china so you look at this here i
was actually a little bit surprised when
i saw this actually because even for
some of the sea options for the lighter
products it's actually going to be
cheaper across the board to actually
ship directly from china whereas for
these slightly heavier products as you
see it's actually cheaper than using
something like dhl to actually ship
directly from
china versus shipping it to the us first
now obviously for this option this
economy air is a little bit cheaper for
this type of product but still it's only
15 cents cheaper so it's very very
similar now obviously if you're able to
actually use c that's where you're going
to be able to see a lot of the bigger
differences but you know these are going
to take so much longer i mean this is
like you're assuming you're adding like
60 days to the lead time you're adding
45 days of lead time from these options
right and even these air options these
are options you're still adding you know
something like 7 to 14 days for dhl
sometimes for a larger order or you know
couple weeks for economy air now some of
you might think oh like it doesn't take
as long as that like yes well
try it out with a bulk order if you're
sending a sample va via dhl then it's
pretty fast right but if you're sending
out thousands of units
via dhl or something like ups or or air
freight line you're going to have to
clear custom it's going to make it to
your location like it's you should be
assuming 7 to 14 days or so or longer
for even air now
as you see these costs like they're not
that different like especially using air
mostly it's cheaper sending from china
than sending it to your local 3pl and
there's also going to be
you know for c yes that's where you get
more savings however you're going to
have to worry about the lead times like
we just discussed
one other thing though is that that's
assuming no customs all right if you're
sending thousands of units you're gonna
have to worry about customs now
traditionally
on average you might be worrying about
like a 25 custom rate on the cogs
themselves so if we assume that that
plugs in these numbers so if you
actually assume customs and import taxes
then the calculation is entirely
different even some of the faster c
options get more expensive
than if you actually ship directly from
china and if you ship directly from
china because it's shipped one package
at a time you're not actually paying the
customs fee on a per order because
that's just how direct from china
shipping works so if you include uh
customs and if you include uh freight
and you actually do the math then you'll
see that actually shipping from china
can be cheaper even in some of the sea
freight options and it's obviously a lot
more flexible and the shipping times are
going to be close enough and don't
forget that you have to actually get the
goods and consider this freightly time
to get to your 3pl and start fulfilling
in the first place and you know even if
your customs rate is like say 15
it's still cheaper to ship from china
compared to something like air freight
don't forget that also if you're using a
usbl there's additional fees as well
there are usually warehouse fees you
know uh you have the storage fees here
per bin per shelf per pallet now
traditionally for us and a lot of china
fulfillment we don't really
charge for warehousing if your inventory
turns like within 60 or 90 days
because
space is a lot cheaper in china to be
completely honest right so you got to
consider for these costs as well and
then uh usually
something is shipped out they actually
charge a receiving fee as well which we
usually don't so these are costs that we
didn't even consider but if you add
those up that's actually going to add to
your cost as well now so that's u.s
fulfillment to the u.s now let's take a
look at international shipping let's
look at international from the u.s so
let's say to the uk yeah this is crazy
actually so uh just using the uk as an
example this is ship shipping
internationally uh it's gonna be almost
eleven dollars for the 30 gram product
uh pretty similar for the 140 gram
product and 17 for the 550 gram product
and the shipping time is gonna be weeks
i mean it's super inefficient it's going
to take a while whereas uh uk shipping
directly from china just look at these
prices i i'm not even going to put an
equation to check this map here but this
is all cheaper even if you're using the
express service that's actually four to
eight days the uk
these are significantly cheaper than
shipping from the us the uk so this is
also what i mean by you can ship
globally and open up entire markets much
more profitably
uh shipping from china then from the us
i forgot to mention this is by the way
excluding freight this is literally if
you ask shipboard how much does it cost
to ship from their 3pl to the uk these
are the prices this is not even
including the freight option because
there's no point because we already know
it's so much cheaper so this is the math
this is the real math um if you're not
convinced yet i i definitely advise you
to check with your own freight costs
check with your own 3pl costs if you're
using a usbo and you know just you know
see what the costs are and you know if
you want to talk to us and kind of
figure out like how our costs compare
for your specific product definitely
reach out below all right so let's now
talk about a brief history of china
shipping and fulfillment and why it's
gotten so efficient recently and i like
to repeat you know this is not just drop
shipping just because you're shipping
from china doesn't actually mean you're
drop shipping we have a lot of clients
actually most of our clients actually
work with us who don't drop ship at all
and they actually just control their
stock and customize their products and
use us for fulfillment that said the
rise of efficient china shipping
really came from the initial boom in
drop shipping and just platforms like
aliexpress shipping to customers
directly around the world because of
that in the last couple years in the
last five six years or so that's when
coilers like unit express and 4px and
ubi really started or refined their
direct shipping services and they gotten
much more efficient in terms of
consistency in terms of times and in
terms of cost as well and now you're
going to be able to actually send you
know to the us for example as fast as
five to ten calendar days very
consistently and in a very cost
effective manner and actually currently
unixpress for example the majority of
their volume is not actually supporting
drop shipping
guess what the most of their volume
actually consists of
it's actually amazon fbm so they
actually do the biggest portion of their
business for amazon fbm which is one of
the most strict in terms of shipping
time and efficiency requirements and in
fact although e-commerce started our
business in drop shipping a couple years
ago
now virtually none of our clients we
work with in a traditional drop shipping
model more than 60 of our clients they
control their own stock they work with
their own factories and they just send
stock to us for uh fulfillment and the
other 40
we do manage some of their supply chain
we help them source and develop products
uh but but still you know none of our
clients are actually working in the
traditional drop shipping anymore so
definitely china fulfillment does not
mean drop shipping in this case although
obviously drop shipping in general help
china fulfillment develop and make it
more efficient and it was through this
experience that i realized through the
years of just just how powerful just
being able to fulfill from china and
more recently actually we've had a lot
more brands who have never really used
china fulfillment like they never drop
before they never even considered
china fulfillment before but because of
all the benefits in terms of flexibility
and cost they are now actually uh much
more shifting to the idea of china
fulfillment and we have some clients who
were 100 u.s fulfillment and now they're
100 china fulfillment for all of the
benefits all right so now let's talk
about some tips and actually how to best
leverage china fulfillment for your
business
so first of all
i hope that we clear the fact that
there's nothing wrong with china
fulfillment there's a lot of benefits to
it i know the last couple years partly
because of the kova supply chain
disruptions there's been a lot of
thinking that you have to
invest in u.s fulfillment local
fulfillment to actually scale up i mean
that's absolutely not true and it's kind
of the opposite as well and especially
if you're currently using china
fulfillment i would seriously seriously
reconsider if it actually makes sense
for you to invest in u.s fulfillment or
local fulfillment unless you're doing so
much volume that you can actually fill
up containers and just constantly send
containers to your local 3pl which is
then when it starts to make more sense
now obviously there are some obvious
benefits
in fulfilling from the us first if you
really want like two-day express
shipping you're not gonna get that from
china it's just literally physically
impossible so if you want that and pay a
lot more for it then of course you
probably want some u.s fulfillment as
well another benefit is that it can
definitely help you to have u.s
fulfillment or local fulfillment during
times where it's just not feasible to
fulfill from china chinese holidays for
example during chinese new year's
any other supply chain disruptions if
you don't want to you know wait the 10
days that
there are going to be logistics pauses
from china during chinese new year if
you are actually able to book full
containers and constant full containers
and you have a great way to project your
volume to be able to have that make
sense with less risk then it certainly
makes sense and then finally there's
simply certain products that just can't
be fulfilled from china stuff that's
more sensitive
dangerous goods stuff that's oversized
or very heavy they just don't make sense
to actually ship from china however
though
i want to emphasize this that the
decision doesn't have to be binary it
doesn't have to be
one or the other if it makes sense for
you i think that one potential optimal
is that especially if you can actually
have enough volume to fill up containers
on c what you can do is actually send
occasional containers uh to get the best
average cost possible because if you can
fill up a container that's how you can
get the best class possible now you
don't have to over stock you can under
stock actually because then you have a
backup plan
from your china fulfillment center and
if you're waiting for your container to
arrive or you run out of stock then you
can continue to actually ship from china
for a slightly more expensive cost
obviously but still you're getting the
average cost savings from those
containers that you're sending to your
3pl and of course anywhere else in the
world uh international shipping is going
to be really bad from 3pls locally so
everything else in the world in europe
uk whatever that's where you're shipping
from china directly and by the way if
you're not doing that already if you're
not shipping around the world and
marketing around the world because
you're stuck with a
consider it like we have some clients
who are stuck to u.s markets and as soon
as they were able to market and shift
international markets their sales would
increase by like 30 40 50 immediately
because it opens up entire new markets
for them and by the way this is
something that actually we at ecomops
are actually planning for this year we
do actually plan to have a mixed model
where we have our own u.s fulfillment
center and we help you organize freight
and we also help you ship directly from
china as well so you get the best of
both worlds so look out for that
in the second half of 2022. now if you
are doing something like this if you're
using a mixed model then there's a
couple key points that you really need
to be aware of you have to have a great
system to really figure out who is
actually fulfilling from where now i
think most us gpl's are going to be able
to do this and at least we at e-comm ops
can do this as well
but we do a lot of technical development
to make this happen but what you can do
is say hey uh your u.s orders for
example are only shipped through your
us-3pl and we only ship your
international orders and if your u.s gpl
runs out of stock you tell us through
some systems starting at an order number
that we fulfilled then to
you know the u.s while you're waiting
for stock and the opposite when you have
u.s stock that has arrived that we pause
at a certain order number another way
that you can do it is you can actually
set different types of shipping methods
in shopify for example uh for different
types of options for example if you have
a
express option that only ships in the us
just call it like two to five day
express whatever it is and then we can
actually ignore anything that has a
shipping option and only ship your
standard shipping from china and some
additional tips to
work with a fulfillment center from
china a first one is location is
incredibly important
you really want to work with a
fulfillment center that's based in
shenzhen i've talked about other videos
about this in my urine express videos
but shenzhen is by far the most
efficient location for international
shipping from china because its
proximity to hong kong and most of the
major couriers have headquarters there
so do not use a fulfillment center
that's based anywhere else if you want
the most efficient shipping one
important point is that with your
fulfillment center in china make sure
you communicate the product i really
send a sample to them before you
actually start shipping out because
there are going to be certain cases
where there are going to be issues with
shipping a particular product
it might be not shippable where it has
to use a special line if it has liquids
for example so if you want no surprises
definitely communicate with your
fulfillment center beforehand make sure
they actually have a real warehouse i
mean uh there are a bunch of smaller
previous drop shipping agents that are
getting into fulfillment right now and
they don't really have a warehouse if
you want to scale and get all the
benefits of this process you can't be
working with someone that is just you
know fulfilling out of their bedroom or
their garage for example make sure that
they actually have a quick and accurate
receiving process we normally just can
receive like tens of thousands of units
in like a day or like half a day but if
that requires a lot of labor though but
if your fulfillment center takes like
three days to process something then it
completely defeats the purpose of how
fast the lead time is so make sure they
have a very efficient receiving process
that they can just receive goods and
start processing the next day make sure
that you
really understand and work with your
fulfillment center to understand all of
the different
shipping methods and communicate that
effectively with your customers as well
i mean just one quick example is that
unixpress has like i mean technically it
has like 10 different lines right not
all of them are relevant to you there's
probably three lines that really make
sense for the average e-commerce brand
however you know a lot of suppliers they
don't really tell you that they just
have one version called the express for
example so you really need to work with
your supplier understand all the
different options because they cost
differently they can send different
things and they have different speeds as
well and that's going to be really
important for you to understand these
options and obviously
manage those expectations and shipping
times to your customers and also
have the most cost efficiency in
choosing the right line that's it for
this video hope that was helpful guys i
really think that more and more china
fulfillment is going to get ever more
efficient and it's really a great option
to ship all of your orders or at least
supplement your local fulfillment if
that's something that you're using right
now and if you are interested in working
with e-comm ops you know we do have an
moq of you know 30 waters per day you
know so if you are interested in working
with us please let us know and i'll
leave the link below and if we're a good
fit then we'll definitely get back to
you and start the process join our
facebook community for the most
up-to-date news on supply chain and
logistics discussions we also have a
free course as well on the entire supply
chain in china so i'll link to that
below until next time this is dalia from
ecom ops see you guys later